From 1914 to 1918,
西 元 1914 到 1918 年
World War I was waging in Europe.
第 一 次 世 界 大 戰 在 歐 洲 進 行
After the war ended
戰 爭 結 束 後
the four great empires disintegrated.
四 大 帝 國 解 體
A trend of national consciousness
全 世 界 瀰漫
dominated the world.
一 種 民 族 自 覺 的 思 潮
A quarter of a century has passed
台 灣 在 日 本 殖 民 統 治 之 下
since Taiwan has lived under Japan's colonial rule.
已 經 過 了 四 分 之 一 個 世 紀
It was the beginning of the
而 日 本 國 內 也 進 入 了
Taisho Democracy in Japan.
開 放 的 大 正 民 主 時 代
In Taiwan,
在 台 灣
an assimilation policy was being carried out.
則 開 始 推 行 內 地 延 長 主 義
There was a group of young Taiwanese men
這 時 候 有 一 群
born around 1895,
在 1895 年 前 後 出 生 成 長 的
who were studying in Japan at the time.
台 灣 留 日 青 年
The exposure to a new
由 於 在 日 本 吸 收 到
culture and new thinking
新 文 化 和 新 思 潮
had aroused their national consciousness.
激 發 了 他 們 潛 在 的 民 族 意 識
Meanwhile in China,
加 上 同 一 段 時 間
the people overthrew the Qing Empire.
中 國 人 民 已 經 推 翻 了 清 帝 國
Eight years later
八 年 後 又 發 生 了
came the influential May Fourth Movement.
影 響 深 遠 的 五 四 運 動
An independence movement also broke out in Korea.
朝 鮮 也 爆 發 獨 立 運 動
All these events further stimulated
這 一 切 都 刺 激 了
these young Taiwanese intellectuals.
這 批 年 輕 的 台 灣 知 識 份 子
Law 63 treats the people of Taiwan
六 三 法 把 所 有 的 台 灣 國 民
as second class citizens.
都 當 作 是 二 等 國 民
We've done everything we could to abolish it
我 們 想 盡 辦 法 要 把 它 廢 除
without any success.
到 現 在 都 還 沒 有 成 功
We must think of a way
我 們 一 定 要 想 個 辦 法
to raise people's awareness about this problem.
讓 大 家 來 重 視 這 個 問 題
The May Fourth Movement in China
僑 中 國 的 五 四 運 動
and the March 1st Movement in Korea
和 朝 鮮 的 三 一 運 動
are great inspiration for us.
對 我 們 都 是 很 大 的 鼓 勵
I think that we,
我 在 想
the Taiwanese people,
我 們 台 灣 人
should have our own organization.
懋 該 要 有 我 們 自 己 的 組 纓
Only then can we have power, right?
這 樣 才 有 力 量 ， 對 不 對
Mr. Lin...
林 先 生 …
You're all here.
大 家 都 在 這 裡 喔
Look...
你 們 看
Today's newspaper.
今 天 的 新 聞
Listen.
大 家 聽 聽 看
U.S. President Wilson has announced his advocacy
美 國 總 統 威 爾 選
of self-determination by ethnic groups.
發 表 弱 小 民 族 自 決 宣 言
At the end of the 19th century,
十 九 世 紀 末 期
the Japanese society was influenced
日 本 社 會 受 本 社 會 受 到
by thoughts in the world.
世 界 性 思 潮 的 影 響
Ideas of freedom and democracy began to spread.
自 由 ， 民 主 的 觀 念 盛 行
Socialism began to sprout.
社 會 主 義 思 想 閔 始 萌 芽
Around the time of World War I,
第 一 次 世 界 大 戰 前 後
the cry for national self-determination was loud.
民 族 自 決 的 呼 聲 高 漲
More than 2000 Taiwanese students
這 時 在 東 京 的
studying in Japan at the time
兩 千 多 名 台 灣 留 學 生
were impacted by these thoughts
需 到 這 些 怒 潮 的 衝 擊
and began to take notice of political issues at home.
開 始 關 心 台 灣 島 內 的 政 治 問 題
This is a chance for national self-determination.
自 由 的 民 族 自 決 機 會
The independence and full sovereignties of
巴 爾 幹 各 國 之 獨 立 與 主 權 完 整
all Balkan countries are guaranteed.
由 國 際 予 以 保 證
Look here.
看 這 裡
Ireland and Korea
愛 爾 蘭 ， 朝 鮮
these colonies intend to become independent
一 些 殖 民 地 都 打 算 要 獼 立
and to break away from the colonial rule.
脫 離 殖 民 統 治
Why can Korea
為 什 麼 一 樣 是 殖 民 地 的 朝 鮮
become an independent country
可 以 獨 立
and we can't?
我 們 為 什 麼 不 行
Yeah...
對 啊 …
From the looks of things,
以 現 在 的 情 形 看 來
I feel that global trends
我 是 覺 得 世 界 的 潛 流
are working in our favor.
是 對 我 們 有 利 的
As long as we work hard
只 要 我 們 打 拼
and stick together,
團 結 起 來
we can do it, too.
我 們 一 定 也 做 得 到
Yes...
對 …
Mr. Lin is right.
林 先 生 說 得 沒 錯
We must follow global trends.
我 們 現 在 就 要 跟 上 世 界 的 潮 流
Taiwanese people must not be the second class citizens.
台 灣 人 民 不 能 當 二 等 國 民
Right...
對 …
So how we must discuss
所 以 我 們 現 在 要 討 論 一 下
what methods we are going to use
看 要 用 什 麼 方 式
to address our rights
才 能 對 台 灣 的 政 府
to the Taiwanese government.
提 出 我 們 要 的 權 利
In 1919, Korea's independence movement
1919 年 朝 鮮 爆 發 獨 立 運 動
shocked the Japanese government and its people.
霖 撼 日 本 朝 野
After Prime Minister Hara took office,
原 敷 內 閣 上 台 後
he proposed an assimilation policy
提 出 了 內 地 延 長 主 義
to treat colonies as extensions of Japan
把 殖 民 地 當 作 日 本 本 土 的 延 伸
and to assimilate the people of these lands
伐 圖 把 殖 民 地 的 異 民 族
into the Japanese culture.
同 化 為 日 本 民 族
We should focus on this point
我 們 丑 姜 從 這 個 角 度 下 去 思 考
in our fight for the rights of our people.
去 扭 濂 爭 取 台 灣 人 的 權 利
Mr. Tsai.
蔡 先 生
Mr. Lin.
林 先 生
You're all here.
你 們 來 了
In 1920, a group of Taiwanese students
1920 年 東 京 地 區 的 台 灣 青 年
in Tokyo founded the New People Association.
成 立 新 民 會
They wanted to find a way
他 們 關 心 台 灣 人 妖 何 才 能
to release Taiwanese people
從 政 治 的 不 平 等 待 遇 中
from political injustice.
解 放 出 來
Its founding is credited to
這 個 會 的 組 成 得 歸 功 於 兩 位
the dedication and hard work
經 常 往 ﹥ 常 往 來 東 京 的 台 灣 仕 紳
of Lin Hsien-Tang and Tsai Hui-Ju,
林 獻 堂 與 蔡 悲 如 的
who frequently traveled to Tokyo for the cause.
熟 心 奔 走 與 串 聯
I oppose treating Taiwan as an extension of Japan.
我 完 全 反 對 內 地 延 長 主 義
Needless to say,
不 用 多 說
it is just
想 也 知 道
an assimilation policy.
這 根 本 就 是 一 種 同 化 主 義
It's simple.
很 簡 單
They want to turn us
他 們 就 是 想 將 我 們 台 灣 人
into one of them.
變 成 日 本 人
That's right.
沒 錯
So we advocate treating
所 以 我 們 主 張
Taiwan as an unique entity.
台 灣 有 台 灣 的 特 殊 性
We must ask the Japanese government
我 們 就 要 先 向 常 國 政 府 要 求
to establish a parliament in Taiwan
在 台 灣 設 立 有 立 法 權
to make laws and to review budget.
預 算 審 查 權 的 台 灣 議 會
Yes.
委
Very good.
很 好
In 1920,
1920 年
these men published The Taiwan Youth
這 群 人 一 邊 發 行 台 灣 青 年 雜 誌
to publicize their ideas of reformation
宣 傳 改 革 的 理 念
while carrying out a 14-year long petition
一 方 面 展 開 長 達 十 四 年 的
for the establishment of a parliament in Taiwan
台 灣 議 會 設 置 請 願 運 動
to fight for the right to self-rule.
爭 取 自 3 自 治 的 權 利
They elected Lin Hsien-Tang as their first chairman.
他 們 推 舉 林 獻 堂 出 任 首 屆 會 長
They also returned to Taiwan on their holidays.
同 時 利 用 返 鄉 假 期
They went to different places in Taiwan
在 台 灣 各 地 進 行 遊 說
to persuade people to support them.
以 爭 取 更 多 人 的 支 持
Please support the idea of setting up a parliament.
請 支 持 台 灣 人 的 議 會 運 動
Please.
﹣ 泰
Go! Go!
加 油 ， 加 油
Sign here.
這 邊 簽 名
Please support the idea of setting up a parliament.
請 支 持 台 灣 人 的 議 會 運 動
Please.
﹣ 泰
The Governor-General to Taiwan
現 在
holds legislative power in his left hand
台 灣 總 督 巨 手 抓 立 法 權
and administrative power in his right.
右 手 握 行 政 權
His actions violate the Constitution of the Japanese Empire.
這 是 達 反 帝 國 憲 法 精 神 的
Aren't Taiwanese human beings?
我 們 台 灣 人 一 樣 是 人 不 是 嗎
Why aren't we protected by the Constitution?
為 什 麼 就 沒 有 受 到 憲 法 的 保 障
Legislative power should be
懋 該 將 立 法 權
returned to the Taiwanese.
還 給 台 灣 人 民 才 對
Am I right?
大 家 說 對 不 對
You are right.
對 …
So we demand the setting up of a parliament.
所 以 我 們 要 求 設 置 台 灣 議 會
The situation in Taiwan is different from that in Japan.
台 灣 的 情 況 跟 日 本 國 內 不 一 樣
It needs separate legislation
需 要 特 別 立 法
and the people of Taiwan
也 雷 要 由 台 灣 人
should be able to review its own budget.
自 己 來 審 查 預 算
Right.
對 …
For 14 years since 1921,
從 1921 年 起 的 十 四 年 間
15 such petitions
台 灣 議 會 設 置 請 願 行 動
were organized.
共 舉 辦 了 十 五 次
Even though no concrete results were achieved,
雖 然 都 沒 有 具 體 的 成 果
the petitioners received great publicity
但 是 當 請 類 團 拗 達 日 本 時
on their visits to Japan.
都 造 成 很 大 的 宣 傳 效 果
Each time when returning to Taiwan,
而 請 願 代 表 們 回 到 台 灣 時
they were supported
也 一 次 比 一 次
strongly by people.
更 加 受 到 民 眾 的 熟 恬 支 持
This continuous action
這 種 持 續 的 請 願 活 動
deeply affected the Japanese government.
深 深 刺 激 著 日 本 政 府
Finally, at the end of 1923, the prosecution of violators
終 於 在 1923 年 底
of the Public Order and Police Law took place.
發 生 了 治 議 事 件
The Office of Taiwan Governor-General
總 督 府 針 對 運 動 活 躍 份 子
conducted a large-scale arrest of these activists.
進 行 一 場 大 進 捕
This was how Tsai Pei-Huo
蔡 培 火 對 於 治 譬 事 件
described this incident.
曾 經 姜 此 描 述
On the morning of December 16, 1923,
1923 年 12 月 16 日 清 早
policemen all over Taiwan
全 台 灣 的 警 察
searched the houses
到 全 台 灣 灣 的 請 類 連 署 人 中
of key petitioners.
重 要 成 員 的 家 宅 中 進 行 搜 查
Some were arrested
有 些 人 被 常 起
and over 60 people were reported to the authorities.
六 十 多 人 遭 到 檢 舉
It shocked the people of Taiwan.
轟 動 了 全 台 的 民 心
This incident had great impact
此 事 件
on the imperial government.
在 日 本 中 央 產 生 巨 大 反 懋
So the administration officials in Taiwan
致 使 台 灣 當 灣 當 局 不 敢 一 意 孫 行
do but reduce the number of the accused.
縮 小 被 檢 舉 人 的 範 圍
Chiang Wei-Shui and I were imprisoned for 4 months,
最 後 蔣 渭 水 和 我 被 監 禁 四 個 月
which was the severest sentence.
判 刑 最 重
But these people
但 是 這 這 些 人
were not defeated.
並 沒 有 因 此 意 到 打 擊
On the contrary, their morale was raised.
士 氣 反 倒 更 加 提 升
After their release,
出 獄 後
they continued the petition.
繼 續 推 動 設 立 議 會 的 請 願 活 動
The island of Formosa is beautiful.
蓬 萊 美 島 真 可 愛
Our ancestors settled down here.
祠 先 基 業 在
We cultivate the land and plant the trees.
田 園 阮 開 樹 阮 栽
We work hard from one generation to the next.
勞 苺 代 過 代
You must understand.
著 理 解 ， 著 理 解
We are pioneers.
阮 是 開 拓 者
We are not ignorant slaves.
不 是 意 奴 才
Hurry, Taiwan, to rule yourself.
自 洽 快 台 灣 全 島
We have the right to manage the public affairs.
公 事 阮 掌 是 憶 該
While the Petition for
就 在 台 灣 議 會 設 置 請 願 運 動
the Establishment of a Taiwan Parliament
在 全 島 各 地
was taking place throughout the island,
泛 沸 揚 揚 推 動 的 同 時
Chiang Wei-Shui, a doctor at Tataocheng,
大 稷 埕 的 執 業 醫 生 蔣 渭 水
made a diagnosis of Taiwan.
為 台 灣 社 會 做 了 診 斷
On first consultation,
最 初 診 察 患 者 時
the patient is found to have a large skull,
困 為 其 頭 較 身 大
which would signify that he is a thinking person.
照 理 說 廳 該 很 有 思 考 力
But a test of common sense proved
但 以 二 三 個 常 識 問 題 詢 問 之 後
his answers are irrelevant.
其 回 答 卻 不 得 要 領
It is evident the patient is feebleminded.
可 見 患 者 是 一 個 低 脊 兒
Even though he has a large skull,
頭 骨 雖 大
he does not have any ideas.
但 是 內 容 空 虧
Chiang Wei-Shui wrote a prescription for Taiwan.
蔣 渭 水 為 台 灣 社 會 開 了 處 方
He believed the viable solution
認 為 根 本 的 解 決 之 道
lied in cultural movements.
就 要 從 文 化 運 動 做 起
In October of 1921,
1921 年 10 月
with the support of Lin Hsien-Tang,
蔣 渭 水 取 得 林 獻 堂 的 支 持
Chiang Wei-Shui founded Taiwan Culture Association
於 台 北 靜 修 女 中
at Blessed Imelda Girls High School.
成 立 台 灣 文 化 協 會
What the Taiwanese suffer from
台 灣 人 所 患 的 症 狀
is a severe case of information deficiency
是 嚴 重 的 知 識 營 養 不 良 症
It can only be cured by
除 非 服 用 大 量 的 知 識 營 養 補 品
a large dose of knowledge supplements.
不 然 是 不 可 能 痊 瘍 的
And cultural movement is
文 化 運 動
a treatment for the cause of this symptom.
就 是 針 對 這 個 症 狀 的 原 回 療 法
Taiwan Culture Association is an institution
文 化 協 會 就 是 專 門 在 研 究
that conducts research and provides causal treatments.
並 施 行 原 困 療 法 的 機 構
For the sake of the future of the Taiwanese
為 了 我 們 台 灣 人 的 前 途
please continue to support Taiwan Culture Association
請 繼 續 支 持 台 灣 文 化 協 會
Thank you.
多 諶
With the help of Taiwan Culture Association
在 文 化 協 會 的 串 聯 下
men with insight on the island
全 島 各 地 的 有 識 之 士
began to form a network.
逐漸 形 成 網 絡
With ideals and passions,
他 們 燃 燒 著 理 想 與 熟 情
in cities and countryside
不 分 城 市 或 鄉 村
from north to south
從 北 到 南
from west to east,
從 西 到 東
they delivered speeches on cultural issues,
舉 辦 文 化 演 講
gave newspaper readings,
讀 報 活 動
produced cultural dramas,
文 化 劇
showed movies,
播 放 電 影
and offered summer programs.
並 開 辦 夏 季 學 校
They launched the enlightenment movement
點 燃 近 代 台 灣 文 化
of contemporary Taiwan culture.
啟 蒙 運 動 的 烏 火
Our actions may be controlled.
我 們 的 身 體 會 失 去 自 由
Our speeches may also be controlled.
我 們 的 言 論 也 有 可 能 受 到 控 制
What is happiness
對 被 統 治 者 而 言
to the people who are being ruled?
幸 福 是 什 麼
The most important thing is to set one's heart free.
心 的 自 由 為 第 一
If one's heart is not free
如 果 沒 有 心 的 自 由
and one is constrained...
而 又 恭 到 束 縉
Besides lectures
除 了 舉 辦 演 講
and newspaper readings,
讀 報 活 動 外
Taiwan Culture Association also utilize two powerful
文 化 協 會 也 掌 握 了 新 劇 與 電 影
media: dramas and movies.
這 兩 種 有 力 的 近 代 傳 播 方 式
In 1926,
1926 年
Taiwan Culture Association organized a team called
台 灣 文 化 協 會 成 立 電 影 隊
Beautiful Taiwan to show movies.
稱 為 美 台 團
It toured the island showing movies
在 島 內 各 地
to educate the public.
巡 迴 放 映 社 會 教 育 電 影
At the same time, it delivered speeches and
並 藉 此 機 會 進 行 文 化 演 講
commented on political issues.
或 政 論 發 表 的 宣 傳 工 作
We have beautiful villages,
美 麗 村
vast sea and high mountains.
海 闊 山 又 高
Please take this seriously.
大 家 請 認 真
Then we will have a happy life.
生 活 著 美 滿
Look.
大 家 看
A deer is walking in the forest.
一 隻 鹿 在 樹 林 裡 散 步
It's not just taking a walk,
不 過 牠 不 只 是 在 散 步 而 已
but searching for food.
牠 是 在 莊 食
Look.
大 家 看
Even a deer
就 算 是 一 隻 鹿
must fill its stomach
也 要 吃 得 飽
to sustain itself.
日 子 才 過 得 下 去
Getting fed is the basic requirement for one's life
這 是 生 存 的 基 本
Look.
你 們 大 家 看
The people of Taiwan
現 在 台 灣 百 姓 的 生 活
under Japanese rule
在 日 本 政 府 統 治 下
are suffering more and more.
是 一 天 比 一 天 遼 悽 慘
The narrator paused.
辯 士 中 止
Today...
今 日 …
Today a deer is going to
今 日 有 一 隻 鹿
drink water by the creek.
要 去 溪 邊 喝 水
The view is more beautiful than ever.
那 風 景 是 更 加 美 更 加 美 麗
One deer.
一 隻 鹿
Two deers.
兩 隻 鹿
Three deers.
三 隻 鹿 來 了
Everyone is happy.
大 家 是 快 快 樂 樂
In 1927,
1927 年
People's Newspaper of Taiwan,
由 東 京 的 台 灣 留 學 生
published by Taiwanese students in Tokyo,
發 行 的 台 灣 民 報
was finally permitted to circulate in Taiwan.
終 於 獲 准 在 台 灣 發 行
The Taiwan Youth has changed into Taiwan,
這 份 從 台 灣 青 年 ， 台 灣
and then into People's Newspaper of Taiwan.
一 路 改 版 蛻 變 來 的 報 紙
This newspaper mainly explored cultural,
主 要 探 索 台 灣 的 社 會
economic, political, and social problems in Taiwan.
政 治 ， 經 濟 ， 文 化 的 問 題
It also criticized the Japanese rule
對 日 本 的 統 治 提 出 了 批 評
and introduced situations and thoughts in the world.
同 時 也 介 紹 世 界 局 勢 與 思 潮
People's Newspaper of Taiwan worked together with
台 灣 民 報 跟 文 化 協 會 相 輔 相 成
Taiwan Culture Association.
共 同 打 造 了 一 個 前 所 未 有 的
They started an era of cultural enlightenment and cultural awakening.
文 化 啟 蒙 與 鷹 醒 的 年 代
With the success of Russian Revolution of 1917,
隨 著 蘄 聯 革 命 成 功
in the 1920s
1920 年 代
socialism became the mainstream.
社 會 主 義 成 為 世 界 思 潮 的 主 流
More and more young leftists
文 化 協 會 的 參 與 者 當 中
joined Taiwan Culture Association.
工 翳 青 年 也 漸 漸 增 多
The conflict between the left and the right
工 右 兩 派 不 同 路 線 的 矛 盾
finally reached the climax.
終 於 透 漸 白 熟 化
But the interests of
不 遇 無 產 階 級
proletarian farmers and laborers
農 民 跟 工 人 的 利 害 關 係
are different from those of small landholders.
跟 小 地 主 資 本 家 是 不 能 一 致 的
The problem is that class struggle
問 題 是
does not lead to social evolution.
階 級 門 爭 不 是 社 會 進 化 的 原 囡
It is merely a disease
階 級 門 爭 是 社 會 進 化 中
caused by social evolution.
所 產 生 的 一 種 病 症
Yeah.
是 啊
We have high ideals,
我 們 的 理 想 雖 然 高 遠
but we still have to face the reality.
不 過 也 要 考 慮 到 社 會 的 現 實
That's compromising.
這 根 本 就 是 妥 協 主 義 嘉
Mr. Lin.
林 先 生
Sorry. I have to run.
抱 歉 ， 我 先 走 了
In January of 1927,
1927 年 1 月
Taiwan Culture Association split up.
文 化 協 會 正 式 分 裂
The left force headed by
以 連 溶 卿 ， 王 敏 川 為 首 的
Lian Wen-Ching and Wang Min-Chuang
工 派 勢 力
took control of the association.
掌 握 了 文 協 的 主 導 權
Old members such as Lin Hsien-Tang
而 林 獻 堂 ， 蔣 渭 水 等 舊 幹 部
and Chiang Wei-Shui withdrew
則 退 出 文 化 協 會
and founded Taiwan People's Party.
另 組 台 灣 組 台 灣 民 眾 黨
It was Taiwan's first political party.
是 台 灣 史 上 第 一 個 本 土 政 黨
It advocated protecting the rights of the Taiwanese.
主 張 維 護 全 體 台 灣 人 民 的 利 益
The New Taiwan Culture Association
分 裔 後 的 新 文 協
led farm worker's movements.
走 向 農 工 運 動 的 道 路
It directed the leftist movement
主 導 1920 年 代 後 期
in the late 1920s.
台 灣 的 巨 翳 運 動
The development of capitalism in Japan
日 本 的 資 本 主 義
has been the same as that in Europe and America.
已 經 與 歐 美 的 資 本 主 義 合 流 了
The Japanese will surely squeeze
他 們 引 然 會 對 殖 民 地
as much as they can
被 壓 迫 的 民 眾
out of their colonies.
展 開 最 激 恬 的 榨 取 政 策
Taiwanese people,
我 們 台 灣 人 啊
Wake up.
醒 來 吧
And fight.
奮 起 吧
The narrator pauses.
辯 士 中 止
The people of Taiwan,
我 們 台 灣 的 民 眾 啊
look, the battlefield is near.
開 闋 的 時 代 戰 場 已 迫 進 我 們
Listen, the trumpet sounds calling for marching.
進 軍 的 喇 叭 已 經 響 起
Stop!
中 止
Advance!
前 逵
The narrator pauses.
辯 士 中 止
After World War I,
第 一 次 世 界 大 戰 之 後
Japan carried out the economic policy of developing
日 本 實 施 工 業 日 本
an industrial Japan and an agricultural Taiwan.
農 業 台 灣 的 經 濟 政 策
The produce of rice and sugarcane soared
台 灣 稻 米 ， 蔗 糖 產 量 激 增
but Taiwanese farmers couldn't share
可 是 台 灣 農 民 們 卻 無 法 分 享
gains of the economic growth.
這 歪 經 濟 腹 經 濟 成 長 的 果 實
Most of the profits were taken away
絕 大 部 分 的 利 益
by landholders and capitalists.
都 被 地 主 和 資 本 家 拿 走 了
This is terrible.
夜 糟 糕
What did they say?
說 什 麼
They said if some sugarcane did not grow well,
甘 蔗 只 要 被 糖 廠 認 為 不 漂 亮 的
the sugar factory would deduct the amount of the sugarcane.
都 要 扣 重 量
The factory decided how much they deduct.
要 拉 幾 斤 重 由 糖 廠 決 定
There is something wrong with their scale.
糖 廠 的 磅 秤 的 確 有 問 題
The amount of the sugarcane measured by them
他 們 秤 的 重 量
is half of the amount measured by us.
和 我 們 秤 出 來 的 重 量 差 一 半
Every one says sugarcane growers who bring their
大 家 都 說
sugarcane to be measured by the sugar association are fools.
最 傻 的 是 種 甘 蔗 給 會 社 秤
How can this happen?
0 這 種 事
Can they really do this?
世 間 有 這 庄 霸 道 的 嗲
That's right.
就 是 j 酥 呸
Then our hard work for the whole year is wasted.
這 樣 我 們 整 年 的 心 血 就 白 費 了
I get depressed whenever I think about that.
想 到 就 悶
Yeah.
就 是 嘉
We can't live like this.
這 樣 怎 麼 脊 做
In October of 1925,
1925 年 10 月
the sugarcane farmers in Erlin, Changhua area
彰 化 二 林 一 帶 的 蔑 農
stood up to the sugar factory
挺 身 向 糖 廠 爭 取 合 理 權 益
and collided with the Japanese police.
與 日 議 發 生 衝 突
On October 22, more than 30 people from
10 月 22 日 那 天
the sugar association and 7 Japanese policemen
三 十 多 個 會 社 的 人 和 七 個 日 警
took some laborers to cut sugarcane.
帶 著 一 些 苺 力 要 來 刈 甘 蔗
We had more than 100
我 們 這 邊 也 有 一 百 多 個
sugarcane farmers on our side.
種 甘 蔑 的 農 民 在
The farmers group
農 組 的 人
told us to stop them,
叫 我 們 不 要 給 他 們 刈
but they were insistent on cutting sugarcane.
他 們 就 硬 要 刈
So a collision broke out.
兩 邊 就 間 始 發 生 衝 突
The knives of two policemen
這 當 中 二 名 議 察 的 佩 刀
were taken by the farmers.
被 蔑 農 搶 走
The police came the next day.
第 二 天 警 察 就 閞 始 來 抓 人 了
93 people were arrested.
有 九 十 三 個 被 抓 去
They were like bandits.
實 在 像 是 土 匪 一 樣
Bandits.
土 匪
The following year after Erlin Incident,
二 林 事 件 之 後
Association of Taiwanese Farmers, a movement group of
隔 年 全 島 性 的 農 民 運 動 團 體
farmers in Taiwan, was established.
台 灣 農 民 組 合 成 立
It's a beautiful day.
今 天 天 氣 真 好
What are they doing?
他 們 在 做 什 麼 善
Just ignore them.
不 要 理 他 們
It's nothing significant.
都 是 些 無 聊 的 事
Yeah.
就 是 啊
Cheers. Cheers.
乾 杯 ， 乾 杯
1928 was a prosperous year
1928 年 是 台 灣 勞 工 運 動
for labor movements in Taiwan.
蓬 勃 發 展 的 一 年
Guided by Chiang of Taiwan People's Party,
在 台 灣 民 眾 黨 的 蔣 渭 水 推 動 下
labor unions across the island got together
各 地 的 勞 工 團 體 逐 步 串 聯 起 來
and formed Taiwan Laborers Union.
組 成 台 灣 工 友 總 聯 盟
In the meantime,
另 一 方 面
Taiwan Communist Party founded in
在 上 海 法 國 租 界 成 立 的
Shanghai's French Concession
台 灣 共 產 黨
returned to Taiwan to do their activities.
也 返 台 展 開 活 動
They presented the ideas of Taiwanese as a hew people
提 出 台 灣 人 是 個 新 興 民 族
and Taiwan as an independent country.
以 及 台 灣 獨 立 建 國 的 主 張
In 1930,
到 了 1930 年
Yang Chao-Chia went further to form
楊 肇 嘉 進 一 步 組 纓 了
Taiwanese Union of Local Self-Government
自 治 聯 盟 台 灣 地 方
and requested that the Taiwanese should
要 求 開 放 地 方 上 的 選 舉 權
have the right to vote.
給 台 灣 人
At the end of 1935,
1935 年 底
Taiwan finally had
於 舉 辦 了 台 灣 終
its first election for local self-government.
第 一 次 的 ﹁ 地 方 自 治 」 選 舉
In order to have a fair election,
為 了 要 使 一 個 公 正 的 選 舉 出 現
several months before the election,
在 幾 個 月 前
we mobilized all of
我 們 就 已 經 動 員
cadre members of the Union
所 有 自 治 聯 盟 的 幹 部
to cities and countryside
到 州 ， 市 ， 街 ， 庄 展 開 工 作
to instill ideas of justice into people
來 灌 輸 人 民 公 正 的 思 想
so that they know how to cast ballots.
行 使 神 聖 的 一 票
But this first-ever election
不 過 台 灣 史 上 首 次 的 選 舉
in Taiwan was full of flaws
卻 是 充 滿 了 瑕 疵
because the Japanese government only allowed
困 為 日 本 政 府
half of the government officials to be elected and
只 間 放 了 一 半 名 額
the other half still to be nominated by the government.
另 一 半 仍 維 持 官 派
Besides, the voter must be male not younger than 25
此 外 還 規 定 必 須 年 滿 二 十 五 歲
years of age and he should
年 繳 稅 額 五 圓 以 上 的 男 性
pay tax over 5 yuan annually.
才 有 投 票 權
During this period,
這 段 期 間
Chiang Wei-Shui, one of the important leaders of
台 灣 近 代 重 要 的
political and social movements in modern Taiwan,
政 治 社 會 運 動 領 導 者 蔣 渭 水
passed away.
卻 不 幸 逝 世 了
In August of 1931,
1931 年 8 月
6 months after the ban on Taiwan People's Party,
台 灣 民 眾 黨 被 禁 半 年 後
Mr. Chiang succumbed to a cold.
蔣 君 竟 以 風 寒 的 病 過 世
Before his passing,
在 他 過 世 之 前
I traveled up from Tainan to see him.
我 特 地 從 台 南 北 上 去 探 視
We shook hands and cried.
彼 此 握 手 流 淚
He said in a feeble voice,
他 以 微 弱 的 聲 音 說
"Brother Pei-Huo,
培 火 兄
take care and best of luck.”
請 你 保 重 努 力
I said, "Brother Chiang,
我 說 蔣 君
go in peace.
你 安 必 去 吧
I will carry on
同 胞 的 事
the work for our people.
我 會 繼 續 打 拼
Please do not worry."
請 你 安 心
Chiang Wei-Shui passed away at a young age
蔣 渭 水 英 年 旱 逝
and the Taiwanese mourned his death.
台 灣 的 百 姓 普 遍 品 傷
On the day of the funeral,
出 殯 當 天
more than 5000 people showed up to pay tribute.
逄 悼 的 民 眾 超 遇 了 五 千 人
The procession stretched for several kilometers.
逆 葬 隊 伍 綿 延 更 達 數 公 里
His passing seemed
他 的 遇 世
to forecast the end of
彷 彿 預 告 著
the era of enlightenment and awakening.
一 個 啟 蒙 和 蒙 和 覺 醒 時 代 的 結 束
In the 1920s, the Han Chinese
1920 年 代
under the Japanese rule demanded rights of
日 治 下 的 漢 人
political participation with social movements.
以 社 會 運 動 爭 取 參 政 權
But the aborigines living in the mountains
但 是 山 區 的 原 住 民
still lived an oppressed life
還 在 日 本 政 府
under the government's policy of managing
﹁ 恩 威 並 濟 」 的 理 蕃 政 策
the aborigines with kindness and severity.
壓 迫 下 生 活
The Japanese police, in particular,
尤 其 日 本 警 察
tyrannized over the aborigines in every way.
處 處 以 高 壓 姿 態 欺 壓 原 住 民
The resentment and hatred
日 常 生 3 活 所 累 積 的
that accumulated over the years
種 種 不 滿 與 仇 恨
finally caused the Wushe Incident in 1930
終 於 在 1930 年
which shocked the world.
引 爆 了 震 驚 國 際 的 霧 社 事 付
On the morning of October 27,
10 月 27 日 上 午
Mona Rudao, the chief of Mahebo,
馬 赫 坡 頭 目 莫 那 魯 道
led the Seedeq tribe to carry out a surprise attack.
率 領 賽 德 克 族 發 動 突 擊
A sports meeting was taking place
當 時 霽 社 小 學 校 操 場
on the playing field of Wushe Elementary School.
正 在 舉 行 運 動 會
During the flag raising ceremony,
升 旗 典 禮 的 時 候
the Seedeq people in ambush
埋 伏 在 四 周 的 賽 德 克 人
rushed out at once to attack
一 擁 而 上
the Japanese who were present.
攻 擊 在 場 的 所 有 日 本 人
On this battle,
這 一 次 戰 役
132 Japanese were killed,
日 本 人 遇 害 者 一 百 三 十 二 人
215 were wounded,
霙 傷 兩 百 一 十 五 人
and two Taiwanese died.
還 有 兩 名 台 灣 人 遭 誤 殺
When the Office of Taiwan Governor-General got news,
總 督 府 據 報 後
they deployed soldiers and policemen to Wushe.
立 刻 調 動 大 批 軍 警 進 攻 霧 社
Seedeq warriors were forced to hide in caves.
賽 德 克 勇 士 們 被 逼 得 躲 進 山 洞
The Japanese then used air raids
日 本 軍 警 調 動 飛 機 轟 炫
and handbills to persuade them to surrender,
傳 單 勸 降
but to no avail.
都 沒 有 結 果
In the end, blister gas bombs,
後 來 竟 投 擲 國 際 公 法 禁 用 的
banned by the International Law, were dropped,
糜 爛 性 毒 氣 彈
resulting in the painful deaths of a mass of Seedeq people.
造 成 大 批 賽 德 克 人 痛 苺 死 亡
This incident shocked people on the island.
這 個 事 件 震 驚 全 台
Up until December 8th when the suppression ceased,
到 12 月 8 日 鎮 壓 告 一 段 落
a total of 644 Seedeqs died.
賽 德 克 族 死 亡 六 百 四 十 四 人
The Office of Taiwan Governor-General
總 督 府 動 員 軍 隊
mobilized 1563 soldiers,
一 千 五 百 六 十 三 人
1231 policemen,
警 察 一 千 兩 百 三 十 一 人
and 1381 non-combatants.
軍 伕 一 千 三 百 八 十 一 人
Next we have Taiwanese singer Chun-Chun
以 下 是 由 台 語 紅 歌 星 純 純
performing "Dance Age."
要 為 我 們 所 演 唱 的 跳 舞 時 代
In the 1920s,
1920 年 代
after 20 -odd years of Japanese occupation,
日 本 統 治 台 灣 二 十 多 年 之 後
Taiwan gradually became
台 灣 社 會 逐 漸 進 入
a modernized society.
近 代 化 的 社 會
Young men and women who had received Japanese education
愛 過 日 式 教 育 的 年 輕 男 女
began to break away from the bonds of tradition
開 始 脫 離 傳 統 的 束 縛
and yearned for an independent life.
主 張 個 人 的 生 活 自 由
Women in particular
尤 其 是 女 性
finally had a chance
開 始 擁 有 了
to lead a career life.
選 擇 職 業 生 活 的 機 會
Every fashionable man and woman at the time
當 時 時 髦 男 女
were familiar with the slogan
都 流 行 著 一 台 口 號
"New world, free love."
維 新 的 世 界 自 由 戀 愛
In October of 1935,
1935 年 10 月
the Office of Taiwan Governor-General in the name
台 灣 總 督 府
of the 40th anniversary of the Japanese rule,
以 始 政 四 十 週 年 的 名 義
spent a million dollars
耗 資 百 萬 元
on mobilizing more than 10,000 Taiwanese
動 員 萬 餘 名 台 灣 人 參 與 籌 辦
to organize an exhibition.
始 政 四 十 年 紀 念 博 覽 會
At this exposition
透 過 這 場 博 覽 會
the Office of Governor-General well publicized
總 督 府 大 大 的 宣 揚
the promises of a modernized Taiwan.
台 灣 近 代 化 的 光 明 面
It also used this opportunity
也 藉 著 這 個 機 會
to flaunt domestically and internationally
對 台 灣 人 與 國 際 社 會 誇 耀
their accomplishments in Taiwan.
日 本 在 台 灣 的 治 理 成 績
As people's spending power increases,
隨 著 社 會 消 費 能 力 的 提 高
and ideas of sports and recreation emerge,
運 動 和 休 閒 的 觀 念 興 起
there was a surge of parks, western-styled restaurants,
公 園 ， 西 餐 廳
department stores and movie theaters.
百 貨 公 司 ， 戲 院 一 一 出 現
The modernization of the lives of the common people
現 代 化 廠 民 生 活 的 改 變
brought out the lively side
讓 當 5 讓 當 時 的 台 灣 社 會
of Taiwanese society.
呈 現 出 活 潑 面 貌
In order to strengthen the national defense,
為 鞏 固 國 防
we must ensure the empire's position in East Asia
懋 磐 保 常 國 在 東 亞 大 陸 的 地 位
and expand into the South Seas.
並 向 南 方 海 洋 發 展
In the early 1930s,
1930 年 代 初 期
Japanese militarism came to power.
日 本 的 軍 國 主 義 抬 頭
They transformed the existing
他 們 將 原 本
economic policy of
﹁ 農 業 台 灣 」 的 經 濟 政 策
agricultural Taiwan into
轉 變 為
"Agricultural Southeast Asia, Industrial Taiwan.”
﹁ 農 業 南 洋 ， 工 業 台 灣 」
Then in 1936,
緊 接 著 1936 年
the Go-South Policy officially became
南 進 政 策
the national policy of the Japanese Empire.
正 式 成 為 日 本 帝 國 的 國 策
Taiwan became the springboard to the South.
台 灣 成 為 日 本 帝 國 南 進 的 跳 板
In order to meet armament needs,
為 困 慶 戰 備 的 需 要
metal, mechanical, shipbuilding, cement,
台 灣 的 金 屬 ， 機 械 ， 造 船
and chemical industries in Taiwan
水 泥 ， 化 學 等 工 業
developed at a rapid pace.
快 速 發 展 起 來
The industrialization
工 業 化 的 結 果
led to the rapid growth in Taiwanese economy.
台 灣 經 濟 快 速 成 長
In the late 1930s,
1930 年 代 末 期
the per capita income in Taiwan
台 灣 人 平 均 所 得
was 50% more than that in Korea.
比 朝 鮮 多 出 百 分 之 五 十
Taiwan was becoming
台 灣 已 經 算 是
an industrialized society.
邁 向 工 業 化 社 會 了
The Marco Polo Bridge Incident of 1937
1937 年 盧 溝 橋 事 件 爆 發
ignited the war between China and Japan
點 燃 了 中 日 兩 國
that would last for eight years.
持 續 八 年 的 戰 火
In order to have the Taiwanese people
為 了 使 台 灣 人
wholeheartedly on Japan's side,
全 心 全 力 站 在 日 本 這 一 邊
the Office of Taiwan Governor-General
台 灣 總 督 府
aggressively launched the Kominka Movement
積 極 展 開 皇 民 化 運 動
to thoroughly transform
企 圖 徹 底 改 造 台 灣 人
the Taiwanese into Japanese.
成 為 日 本 人
During the Kominka Movement, the Japanese also set up
在 皇 民 化 運 動 時 期
the Main Hall Improvement Movement,
日 本 人 大 力 推 動 正 廳 改 善 運 動
which forced Taiwanese people
規 定 台 灣 人
to replace the deities they originally worshipped
原 來 在 家 裡 正 廳 供 奉 的 神 明
with the Shinto goddess
換 作 日 本 的 祖 先 之 神
Amaterasu.
天 照 大 神
Is this right to put the goddess in this way?
這 樣 放 對 嗎
The colonizers believed that
日 本 殖 民 者 認 為 講 日 語
speaking Japanese was imperative
是 成 為 真 正 的 日 本 人 的
in becoming a real Japanese.
必 要 條 付
So campaigns to make Japanese
因 此 推 動
the national language
社 會 上 講 日 語 的 國 語 運 動
spread like wildfire.
如 火 如 荼 地 展 開
They also encouraged the Taiwanese
同 時 並 鼓 勵 台 灣 人
to use Japanese names.
改 用 日 本 妮 名
I am Kobayashi Sajio.
我 是 小 林 幸 雅
A-Ho.
阿 福 啊
When the Second Sino-Japanese War broke out,
中 日 戰 爭 爆 發 後
Taiwanese men didn't get drafted,
台 灣 人 雖 然 不 用 當 兵
but they went to China
卻 陸 續 以 軍 伕 ， 軍 農 夫
as non-combatants and military farmers,
通 譯 等 名 義
singing military songs
隨 著 由 台 灣 歌 謠 改 成 的 軍 歌
adapted from Taiwanese songs.
去 到 了 中 國 戰 場
Hurry up.
中 ﹣
Dig those trenches.
給 我 好 好 的 挖 据 戰 塵
Yes, sir.
琥 ﹣
This will increase our combat force.
這 樣 才 能 提 升 我 們 的 戰 鬥 力
Hurry up.
快 一 點
Japan thought that the battle in China
在 中 國 作 戰 的 日 本
would end soon.
原 以 為 戰 事 會 速 戰 速 決
They didn't expect to get caught up in it.
沒 想 到 卻 陷 入 中 國 遼 闊 的 戰 場
In order to break through the stalemate,
為 了 突 破 戰 事 膠 著 的 狀 態
Japan decided to wage wars in Southeast Asia
日 本 決 定 轉 移 戰 場
and in areas around the Pacific Ocean,
征 戰 南 洋 和 太 平 洋
which resulted in the Pacific War.
於 是 爆 發 了 太 平 洋 戰 爭
With the expansion of the battlefield,
隨 著 戰 場 的 擴 大
the Japanese changed their policy
為 了 擴 充 軍 源
of not recruiting
原 本 不 雷 要 台 灣 人 當 兵 的 政 策
Taiwanese soldiers.
開 始 轉 變
In 1942,
1942 年 開 始
the Office of Taiwan Governor-General implemented
總 督 府 在 台 灣 實 施
the Special Volunteer Policy,
特 別 志 願 兵 制 度
which brought an upsurge of volunteers.
撚 起 了 社 會 上 志 願 從 軍 的 熟 潮
They set up street stands for people to sign up.
他 們 在 路 邊 擺 攤 子 給 人 簽 名
When a young man walks by,
經 過 的 時 候
a Japanese officer would hold him down and say,
日 本 軍 官 把 人 押 著
"You have a great physique.
問 說 你 體 格 這 麼 好
Are you willing to sacrifice for the state?”
是 不 是 顧 意 為 國 奉 獻
Under the circumstance,
在 那 種 情 形 之 下
one could do nothing but sign up.
沒 辦 法
No one dares to refuse.
誰 敢 擔 當 非 國 民 的 罪 名
Most of the volunteers
參 加 志 願 兵 的 台 灣 青 年
were sent to Southeast Asia
大 部 分 會 被 逆 到 南 洋 的 戰 場
to fight the Americans.
與 美 軍 作 戰
In this year,
這 一 年
the Japanese were beginning
日 軍 已 經 開 始 在 太 平 洋 戰 場 上
to lose their stand in the Pacific battlefields.
節 節 敗 退
The Japanese Army also enlisted Taiwanese aborigines
日 本 陸 軍 也 招 募 原 住 民
to form the Takaza Volunteers,
組 成 高 砂 義 勇 隊
who carried out the most dangerous mission
擔 任 了 比 日 軍 還 危 險
to fight at the battle front.
還 重 要 的 前 線 任 務
Not only the men,
不 僅 男 性 上 戰 場
but also Taiwanese women
台 灣 女 性
were mobilized to serve as nurses.
也 被 動 員 到 戰 場 擔 任 看 護 婦
The Japanese military rounded up comfort women
日 軍 從 各 佔 領 地 ， 殖 民 地
from various occupied and colonized territories
總 集 懲 安 婦
to serve Japanese soldiers in the war zones.
到 戰 區 服 務 日 本 軍 人
Taiwanese women were no exceptions.
台 灣 的 女 性 也 未 能 倖 免
“Brave warriors of the front,
莢 勇 的 前 方 戰 士
ever since the holy battle of Greater East Asia started,
自 大 東 亞 聖 戰 以 來
wherever you have been,
皇 軍 所 到 之 虛
you win all the battles.
連 戰 昏 捷
We have occupied innumerable territories.
現 在 的 領 土 難 以 數 計
This is all thanks
這 都 是 由 於
to your hard work
您 們 無 法 用 言 語 形 容 的
which is beyond description.”
艱 難 辛 勞 而 來 的
In April of 1941,
1941 年 4 月
right before the start of the Pacific War,
太 平 洋 戰 爭 爆 發 前 夕
the Public Service Association of Imperial Subjects was set up.
日 本 成 立 皇 民 奉 公 會
Various secondary groups emerged
在 皇 民 奉 公 會 的 積 極 動 員 下
under its aggressive mobilization.
各 式 各 樣 的 次 級 團 體 爭 相 成 立
Even public school students
連 公 學 校 學 生
were called upon to write letters.
也 被 動 員 去 寫 懲 問 俸
“We at the home front,
在 後 方 的 我 們
like you warriors,
和 各 位 戰 士 一 樣
are busy with our missions
勤 奮 負 起 自 己 的 任 務
and with air-raid drill.
或 是 拼 命 的 接 受 防 室 演 習 記 練
The youth leagues, too, are hard at work.”
青 年 團 們 也 努 力 的 鍛 鍊
“Going to the Shinto shrine to pray
而 每 天 到 神 社 衰 顧
that you may win in battles
各 位 戰 士 武 運 長 久
has become our daily homework.”
也 是 我 們 每 日 必 做 的 課 題 之 一
“We will defend the home front. Do not worry.
我 們 會 堅 守 後 方
Strive to defeat the British and the Americans.
請 安 心 為 擊 敗 莫 美 奮 鬥 吧
Under the Greater East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere,
在 大 東 亞 共 榮 國 的 天 空
the day of justice and glory is approaching.
正 義 光 輝 的 日 子 也 更 近 了
We will pray for you...”
我 們 會 從 台 灣 為 各 位 戰 士
The Battle of Midway in June of 1942
1942 年 6 月 的 中 途 島 之 役
saw Japan's first defeat.
讓 日 軍 首 嘗 敗 纍
The U.S. took the offensive while Japan became defensive.
美 日 雙 方 自 此 攻 守 易 勢
In 1943, the U.S. began counterattacking
1943 年 美 軍 開 始 跳 島 反 攻
as the Japanese continued to retreat.
日 軍 則 是 節 節 敗 退
The battle made a U-turn.
整 個 戰 局 徹 底 扭 轉
Due to heavy loss of troops,
日 本 由 於 兵 力 嚴 重 耗 損
Japan began to draft students into the war.
開 始 徵 調 在 學 學 生 上 戰 場
Taiwan was no exception.
例 外 台 灣 也 不
More than 10,000 students
當 時 甚 至 有 一 批 上 萬 名
ranging from ages 12 to 19
十 二 歲 到 十 九 歲 的
were called to Japan
= 謹 生 台 灣 青 少 年 學
by the Japanese Navy
被 日 本 海 軍
to work in military factories
招 募 到 日 本 本 土 的 軍 事 工 廠
where they were busy with arms production,
從 事 飛 機 ， 魚 雷 ， 飛 彈 等
such as airplanes, torpedoes, and missiles.
武 器 的 製 造 工 作
As the war extended and situations worsened
隨 著 戰 期 延 長 ， 戰 局 吃 緊
regulations such as
為 了 戰 爭 需 要 所 實 施 的
consumption and goods controls,
物 資 管 制 ， 食 物 配 給
and food rationings were implemented,
消 費 管 制 等 種 種 規 定
which affected the lives of the Taiwanese.
也 影 響 到 台 灣 人 的 戰 時 生 活
So small?
這 廖 小 啊
Don't you have anything else?
沒 別 的 嗚
We're using this money to buy planes.
這 是 要 用 來 買 飛 機 的
If a leg wound gets infected,
若 是 腿 上 有 一 個 傷 口 受 到 感 桃
it never gets better.
就 永 遠 好 不 了
Everyday tons of patients
毐 天 都 有 成 群 的 病 人
wait in line to be treated.
排 隊 等 待 治 療
Lifting the trouser leg, you see a lot of maggots.
褲 管 一 打 開 就 看 到 一 大 堆 蛆
It's very scary.
非 常 的 惡 怖
In 1944,
1944 年
Taiwan, originally being
履 本 只 作 為 日 本 本 土
a liaison stronghold
與 南 洋 戰 場 聯 絡 據 點 的 台 灣
for the Southeast Asian battlefields,
開 始 轉 成 為
became the front line of the Japanese defense.
防 衛 日 本 本 土 的 第 一 線 戰 地
On September 1st, the Office of Taiwan Governor-General
9 月 1 日 總 督 府 正 式 宣 布
announced the implementation of a draft system in Taiwan.
在 台 灣 實 施 徵 兵 制
More than 80,000 Taiwanese
總 計 太 平 洋 戰 爭 中
fought for Japan in the Pacific War.
有 八 萬 多 名 台 灣 人 當 了 日 本 兵
And more than 120,000 were enlisted
而 被 徵 為 軍 屬 ， 軍 伕 的 人 數
as civilian employees and non-combatants.
至 少 有 十 二 萬 餘
Chen Chien-Wu, a poet,
詩 人 陳 千 武 是 太 平 洋 戰 爭 時
was a young volunteer from Taiwan.
被 徵 召 為 志 願 兵 的 台 灣 青 年
In "Pigeon,"
透 過 信 鴨 這 首 詩
he expressed a deep mourning
他 向 不 幸 戰 死 的 台 灣 兵
for the Taiwanese soldiers who died in the war.
表 達 了 深 沉 的 悼 念
This Greater East Asia crusade
日 本 這 場 大 東 亞 聖 戰
took the lives of
總 計 奪 去 了
more than 30,000 Taiwanese.
三 萬 多 條 台 灣 人 寶 貴 的 性 命
After the Second World War,
二 次 大 戰 後
the KMT took over Taiwan.
接 收 台 灣 的 國 民 黨 政 府
What was once an enemy state
又 從 台 浣 台 籍 日 本 兵 眼 中 的 敵 國
became the fatherland to the Taiwanese Japanese soldiers
變 成 祖 國
who thus became confused.
造 成 台 灣 兵 的 迷 惘
Who am I fighting for?
我 到 底 為 誰 而 戰
What am I fighting for?
為 何 而 戰
Did we lose
我 們 到 底 是 輸 了
or did we win?
還 是 羶 了
Even years after the war,
即 使 在 戰 爭 結 束 多 年 後
these questions still
這 些 唱 號 仍 然 在 他 們 的 夢 魘 中
surfaced in their nightmares
載 浮 載 沅
and would never go away.
揮 之 不 去
Defense-in-depth paired with guerilla warfare...
縱 深 防 禦 配 以 游 擊 戰
At the end of 1943,
1943 年 年 底
The Allies began to take the offensive
太 平 洋 戰 場 上
on the Pacific battlefield.
盟 軍 開 始 轉 守 為 攻
Taiwan became the landing target for the Americans.
台 灣 也 成 了 美 軍 登 陸 的 目 標
The Office of Taiwan Governor-General prepared for war in Taiwan.
總 督 府 開 始 在 台 灣 積 極 備 戰
They planned to fight until the last
準 備 戰 到 最 後 一 人
moment when every one was killed and all arms were
最 後 一 彈
used up to protect the safety of Japan proper.
用 來 力 保 日 本 本 土 的 安 全
In the autumn of 1944,
1944 年 秋 天
Taiwan began to suffer
台 灣 本 島
heavy bombardments from the U.S.
開 始 遭 受 美 軍 的 猛 恬 轟 炸
All manufacturing sectors nearly came to a stop,
各 項 生 產 事 業 幾 乎 面 臨 停 擺
so did industrial developments.
而 工 業 發 展 也 陷 入 停 頓
People were evacuated
都 市 城 鎮 裡 的 人
from cities to the countryside.
紛 紛 疏 散 到 鄉 間
When the air-raid alarm sounded,
當 空 襲 警 報 一 響 起
people hid in air-raid shelters,
人 們 紛 紛 躲 進 防 空 塵
woods or caves.
竹 林 或 山 洞 裡
Not only were they worried about
一 方 面 擔 憂 著 家 園 將 毆 於 戰 火
their homes being destroyed,
一 方 面 徬 徨 於
but also uncertain about the future.
戰 爭 所 牽 動 的 未 來
As the days passed,
隨 著 日 落 月 升
the Taiwanese prayed for the war to end.
台 灣 人 期 待 戰 爭 早 日 結 束
Taiwanese intellectuals in the mid-Japanese Occupation
日 據 時 代 中 期 的 台 灣 知 識 份 子
Era criticized and reflected
對 台 灣 人 的 性 格
on the nature of the Taiwanese.
提 出 了 反 省 和 批 判
In contrast to the Japanese ruling class,
相 對 於 統 治 階 層 的 日 本 人
the people of Taiwan
在 台 灣 的 居 氏
began to call themselves Taiwanese.
開 始 稱 呼 自 己 是 台 灣 人
In the history of Taiwan,
在 台 灣 人 民 歷 史 中
This was the earliest appearance
這 是 最 早 出 現
of Taiwanese consciousness.
台 灣 人 意 識 的 時 代
Just when this consciousness
正 當 台 灣 人 意 論 意 誤 和 台 灣 意 識
began to sprout,
茁壯 發 展 不 久
World War II broke out.
第 二 次 世 界 大 戰 來 臨
The Japanese government accelerated
日 本 政 府 加 速 在 台 灣 推 行
the Kominka policy in Taiwan,
皇 民 化 政 策
hoping to transform Taiwanese into Japanese.
希 望 濂 把 台 灣 人 改 造 成 日 本 人
After years of war,
台 灣 人 度 遇 戰 爭 的 烽 火 歲 月
Japan finally surrendered
終 於 在 1945 年 8 月 15 日
unconditionally on August 15, 1945,
日 本 宣 告 無 條 件 投 降
and the Taiwanese were freed.
而 獲 得 解 放
The Taiwanese consciousness resurfaced
台 灣 意 識 再 次 浮 現
and the claims and pursuits of the Taiwanese were voiced.
台 灣 人 的 主 張 和 追 求 再 次 提 出
This became the main force influencing
而 成 為 二 次 大 戰 後
the development of Taiwan after the Second World War.
主 導 台 灣 去 向 的 重 要 力 量